<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd">
<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>Aero-Graphics, Inc.</origin>
    <pubdate>20190304</pubdate>
    <title>Utah 2018 Lidar - CentralUtah_QL1; Lift: 20180605_N7269T_SN5060410</title>
    <geoform>Lidar point cloud</geoform>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>Product: These Lidar data are unclassified swath LAS 1.4 files, used to create classified LAS 1.4 files and subsequent data.
    Geographic Extent: Northern, Central, and Southern Utah, covering approximately 10,450 square miles; partial coverage of 8 counties covering approximately 1,756 square miles in the Central Utah QL1 AOIs (Park City, Utah County, Wasatch Mountains, Western San Rafael Swell).
    Dataset Description: Utah 2018 Lidar project called for the planning, acquisition, processing, and derivative products of Lidar data to be collected at a nominal pulse spacing (NPS) of 0.35 meters. Project specifications are based on the U.S. Geological Survey National Geospatial Program Base Lidar Specification, Version 1.2. The data was developed based on a horizontal projection/datum of NAD83 (2011), UTM Zone 12, meters and vertical datum of NAVD88 (GEOID12B), meters. Lidar data was delivered as flightline-extent unclassified LAS swaths, as processed Classified LASv1.4 files formatted to 5065 individual 1,000 meter x 1,000 meter tiles; as tiled intensity imagery, as tiled bare-earth DEMs, and as tiled first-return DSMs, tiled with a mix of 1,000 meter x 1,000 meter and 2,000 meter x 2,000 meter schema (1604 tiles). Continuous breaklines were produced in ESRI shapefile format.
    Ground Conditions: Lidar was collected in spring of 2018, while no snow was on the ground and rivers were at or below normal levels. In order to post process the Lidar data to meet task order specifications and meet ASPRS vertical accuracy guidelines, Aero-Graphics, Inc. established a total of 29 ground control points that were used to calibrate the Lidar to known ground locations established throughout the AOI project area. An additional 479 independent accuracy check points, 380 in Bare Earth and Urban landcovers (380 NVA points), 99 in the Shrubs category (99 VVA points), were used to assess the vertical accuracy of the data. These check points were not used to calibrate or post process the data.</abstract>
   <purpose>To acquire detailed surface elevation data for use in conservation planning, design, research, floodplain mapping, dam safety assessments and elevation modeling, etc. Classified LAS files are used to show the manually reviewed bare earth surface. This allows the user to create intensity images, breaklines and raster DEMs and DSMs. The purpose of these Lidar data was to produce high accuracy 3D hydro-flattened digital elevation models (DEMs) with a 0.5 meter cell size. These raw Lidar point cloud data were used to create classified Lidar LAS files, intensity images, 3D breaklines, hydro-flattened DEMs, and first return DSMs as necessary.</purpose>
   <supplinf>State of Utah Contract No. AV2406 Contractor: Aero-Graphics, Inc. Lidar data were acquired and calibrated by Aero-Graphics, Inc. All follow-on processing was completed by the prime contractor.</supplinf>
   <lidar>
    <ldrinfo>
     <ldrspec>USGS-NGP Lidar Base Specification v1.2</ldrspec>
     <ldrsens>Optech Galaxy PRIME</ldrsens>
     <ldrmaxnr>8</ldrmaxnr>
     <ldrnps>0.35</ldrnps>
     <ldrdens>8.0</ldrdens>
     <ldranps>0.35</ldranps>
     <ldradens>8.0</ldradens>
     <ldrfltht>1450</ldrfltht>
     <ldrfltsp>120</ldrfltsp>
     <ldrscana>34</ldrscana>
     <ldrscanr>85.5</ldrscanr>
     <ldrpulsr>550</ldrpulsr>
     <ldrpulsd>3</ldrpulsd>
     <ldrpulsw>1</ldrpulsw>
     <ldrwavel>1064</ldrwavel>
     <ldrmpia>1</ldrmpia>
     <ldrbmdiv>0.25</ldrbmdiv>
     <ldrswatw>887</ldrswatw>
     <ldrswato>20</ldrswato>
     <ldrgeoid>National Geodetic Survey (NGS) Geoid12B</ldrgeoid>
    </ldrinfo>
    <ldraccur>
     <ldrchacc>0</ldrchacc>
     <rawnva>0.113</rawnva>
     <rawnvan>380</rawnvan>
     <clsnva>0.112</clsnva>
     <clsnvan>380</clsnvan>
     <clsvva>0.180</clsvva>
     <clsvvan>99</clsvvan>
    </ldraccur>
    <lasinfo>
     <lasver>1.4</lasver>
     <lasprf>6</lasprf>
     <laswheld>Withheld (ignore) points were identified in these files using the standard LAS Withheld bit.</laswheld>
     <lasolap>Swath "overage" points were identified in these files using the standard LAS overlap bit.</lasolap>
     <lasintr>16</lasintr>
     <lasclass>
      <clascode>0</clascode>
      <clasitem>Created, never classified</clasitem>
     </lasclass>
    </lasinfo>
   </lidar>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <sngdate>
     <caldate>20180605</caldate>
    </sngdate>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>ground condition</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>Complete</progress>
   <update>None planned</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-112.17608372372212</westbc>
    <eastbc>-111.94382160302776</eastbc>
    <northbc>40.447462148658225</northbc>
    <southbc>40.047875846109491</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>None</themekt>
    <themekey>Model</themekey>
    <themekey>LAS Point Cloud</themekey>
    <themekey>Remote Sensing</themekey>
    <themekey>Elevation Data</themekey>
    <themekey>Lidar</themekey>
    <themekey>Hydrology</themekey>
   </theme>
   <place>
    <placekt>None</placekt>
    <placekey>Utah</placekey>
    <placekey>Carbon County</placekey>
    <placekey>Emery County</placekey>
    <placekey>Juab County</placekey>
    <placekey>Salt Lake County</placekey>
    <placekey>Summit County</placekey>
    <placekey>Tooele County</placekey>
    <placekey>Utah County</placekey>
    <placekey>Wasatch County</placekey>
   </place>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>No restrictions apply to these data.</accconst>
  <useconst>None. However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this dataset was collected and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions. Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full awareness of the limitations of the data. Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these data.</useconst>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <logic>Data covers the entire area specified for this project.</logic>
  <complete>These raw LAS data files include all data points collected. No points have been removed or excluded. A visual qualitative assessment was performed to ensure data completeness. No void areas or missing data exist. The raw point cloud is of good quality and data passes Non-Vegetated Vertical Accuracy specifications.</complete>
  <posacc>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>The project specifications require that only Non-Vegetated Vertical Accuracy (NVA) be computed for raw Lidar point cloud swath files. The required accuracy (ACCz) is: 19.6 cm at a 95% confidence level, derived according to NSSDA, i.e., based on RMSE of 10 cm in the "bare earth" and "urban" land cover classes. The NVA was tested with 380 check points located in bare earth and urban (non-vegetated) areas. These check points were not used in the calibration or post processing of the Lidar point cloud data. The check points were distributed throughout the project area and were surveyed using GPS techniques. See survey report for additional survey methodologies. Elevations from the unclassified Lidar surface were measured for the x,y location of each check point. Elevations interpolated from the Lidar surface were then compared to the elevation values of the surveyed control points. AccuracyZ has been tested to meet 19.6 cm or better Non-Vegetated Vertical Accuracy at 95% confidence level using RMSE(z) x 1.9600 as defined by the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy (NSSDA); assessed and reported using National Digital Elevation Program (NDEP)/ASRPS Guidelines.</vertaccr>
    <qvertpa>
     <vertaccv>0.113</vertaccv>
     <vertacce>Tested 0.113 meters NVA at a 95% confidence level using RMSE(z) x 1.9600 as defined by the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy (NSSDA). The NVA of the raw Lidar point cloud swath files was calculated against TINs derived from the final calibrated and controlled swath data using 380 independent check points located in Bare Earth and Urban land cover classes.</vertacce>
    </qvertpa>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>Raw Data and Boresight Processing: The boresight for each lift was done individually as the solution may change slightly from lift to lift. The following steps describe the Raw Data Processing and Boresight process: 1) Technicians processed the raw data to LAS format flight lines using the final GPS/IMU solution. This LAS data set was used as source data for boresight. 2) Technicians first used Aero-Graphics, Inc. proprietary and commercial software to calculate initial boresight adjustment angles based on sample areas selected in the lift. These areas cover calibration flight lines collected in the lift, cross tie and production flight lines. These areas are well distributed in the lift coverage and cover multiple terrain types that are necessary for boresight angle calculation. The technician then analyzed the results and made any necessary additional adjustment until it is acceptable for the selected areas. 3) Once the boresight angle calculation was completed for the selected areas, the adjusted settings were applied to all of the flight lines of the lift and checked for consistency. The technicians utilized commercial and proprietary software packages to analyze how well flight line overlaps match for the entire lift and adjusted as necessary until the results met the project specifications. 4) Once all lifts were completed with individual boresight adjustment, the technicians checked and corrected the vertical misalignment of all flight lines and also the matching between data and ground truth. The relative accuracy was less than or equal to 7 cm RMSEz within individual swaths and less than or equal to 10 cm RMSEz or within swath overlap (between adjacent swaths). 5) The technicians ran a final vertical accuracy check of the boresighted flight lines against the surveyed check points after the z correction to ensure the requirement of NVA = 19.6 cm 95% Confidence Level (Required Accuracy) was met.</procdesc>
    <procdate>2018</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
 </dataqual>
 <spdoinfo>
  <direct>Point</direct>
 </spdoinfo>
 <spref>
  <horizsys>
   <planar>
    <gridsys>
     <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
     <utm>
      <utmzone>12</utmzone>
      <transmer>
       <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
       <longcm>-111.0</longcm>
       <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
       <feast>500000.0</feast>
       <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
      </transmer>
     </utm>
    </gridsys>
    <planci>
     <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
     <coordrep>
      <absres>0.01</absres>
      <ordres>0.01</ordres>
     </coordrep>
     <plandu>meters</plandu>
    </planci>
   </planar>
   <geodetic>
    <horizdn>D_NAD_1983_2011</horizdn>
    <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
    <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
    <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
   </geodetic>
  </horizsys>
  <vertdef>
   <altsys>
    <altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988 (GEOID12B)</altdatum>
    <altres>0.01</altres>
    <altunits>meters</altunits>
    <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
   </altsys>
  </vertdef>
 </spref>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>Utah AGRC</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>physical and mailing</addrtype>
     <address>1 State Office Building, Room 5130</address>
     <city>Salt Lake City</city>
     <state>UT</state>
     <postal>84114</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>801-538-3665</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>agrc@utah.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <resdesc>Owner</resdesc>
  <distliab>In no event shall the creators, custodians, or distributors of this information be liable for any damages arising out of its use (or the inability to use it).</distliab>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20190304</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>Aero-Graphics, Inc.</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
     <address>40 West Oakland Avenue</address>
     <city>Salt Lake City</city>
     <state>UT</state>
     <postal>84115-3007</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>801-487-3273</cntvoice>
    <cntfax>801-487-3313</cntfax>
    <cntemail>agi@aero-graphics.com</cntemail>
    <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 5:00 PM (Mountain Time)</hours>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  <metac>None</metac>
  <metuc>None</metuc>
  <metsi>
   <metscs>None</metscs>
   <metsc>Unclassified</metsc>
   <metshd>None</metshd>
  </metsi>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
